Hey it’s Professor Dave; let’s work with
percentages.
We are all aware of percentages, as they are
ubiquitous in society.
There is a sale today, thirty percent off.
Leave a twenty percent tip after the meal.
Today there is a fifty percent chance of rain.
So what are these things?
Well in Latin, centum means one hundred, so
percent literally means out of a hundred.
It’s just a way of conveying magnitude,
by modifying some total into a hundred, and
then reporting a value of interest as some
fraction of that hundred.
If you get a ninety percent on your math quiz,
you could have gotten nine points out of ten,
eighteen points out of twenty, four hundred
fifty out of five hundred, or any other number
that obeys this ratio of ninety out of a hundred.
Whatever we have to do to the larger number
to make it one hundred, we do that same thing
to the other number.
Ten must be multiplied by ten to get a hundred,
so the nine is also multiplied by ten.
In this way, percentages are ratios, they
are just very specific ratios that compare
numbers to a hundred, because although this
number is totally arbitrary, it is an ideal
size for comparison.
One hundred is small enough that our brains
can easily comprehend its magnitude, but also
large enough that there are sufficient gradations
between zero and a hundred so as to make meaningful
comparisons.
In this way, we can look at percentages as
simple fractions.
Eighty percent is eighty one-hundredths.
We learned how to simplify fractions, so let’s
divide both of these numbers by twenty.
We should get four fifths.
This means that eighty percent and four fifths
are equivalent; they mean the same thing.
Moving to another example, fifty percent is
fifty one hundredths, and dividing both numbers
by fifty, we get one half.
This makes sense, as fifty is half of a hundred.
If you have something like three percent,
that will be three one hundredths, and that
can’t be simplified any further.
We should be able to convert between percentages,
fractions, and even decimals in this way with
relative ease, so let’s check comprehension.